<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Ram Parthasarathy</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/all-en.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2015-07-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Lessons from working for a growth stage startup</title><link href="/lessons-from-working-for-a-growth-stage-startup.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>ram</name></author><id>tag:,2015-07-31:lessons-from-working-for-a-growth-stage-startup.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After spending close to 4 years and 3 months at Monetate, I decided it was time for me to move on.  I joined Monetate, a marketing tech company that builds data-driven products for online retailers and brands as employee number 36 and as an early member of the engineering team.  Monetate was an incredible place to work and everything I know about engineering, product management and the marketing tech industry, I owe it to the job. I wanted to capture my thoughts and more importantly reflect on the things I learned by being a part of a growth stage startup. During my time the headcount, clients, revenue and every other metric grew at a healthy rate and there were a number of ups and downs. Every stage brought along a number of interesting challenges.  Here is what I learned&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Be Thankful&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I graduated, I knew I wanted to work for a startup. I was a few days away from moving to the bay area where I was interviewing with a few companies. Things took a turn and I ended up in suburban Philadelphia to work for a startup that was working on some innovative things in a space that I was interested in.  By the end of the first month, I knew I was going to stay with that startup for a while. I loved the product, the people and I was in fact surprised by all the things I was capable of doing. People say everyone will remember their first job and their first manager. I sure will. I was a blank slate and my manager taught me so many things and truly cared about my career path. More than a manager, he was a great mentor. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the next four years, I had the opportunity to work with several amazing individuals from different departments. I learned a lot from every one of them. I am incredibly thankful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Every single employee can make a difference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the great things about growth stage startups is, every single employee will have the opportunity to make a difference. I was able to see it first hand in several instances where initiatives taken by individuals or small teams had a significant impact on the business. When I say every single employee, I mean it.  Irrespective of the person’s role in the company, the fast-paced collaborative nature of a growth stage startup provides unlimited opportunities for those who are willing to go the extra mile. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Having a good manager has a huge impact&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a startup has less than 50 employees, having a flat structure under a strong leadership team with little hierarchy can do wonders. I truly believe in that system and Monetate adopted that methodology till it was feasible and it worked really well. Once a startup grows and transitions into a traditional management structure, it brings along a million complications. I was lucky that both the managers I had at Monetate were incredibly awesome. My second manager hired me as a product manager and helped me figure out a path for me based on where I want to go. He supported my ambitious and crazy initiatives, gave me interesting problems to solve, tolerated my failures and helped me become a better product manager. In many scenarios, he believed in me more than I believed in myself and that brought the best out of me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A personal rule I have is my manager should be significantly better at what I am trying to get better at. This also applies indirectly to teammates. Unlike engineering teams, product management teams are significantly smaller and in turn are very tightly knit.  PMs in most teams come from different backgrounds and it is great opportunity to learn from each other. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Product management is fun and impactful&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few years as an engineer, I switched over to product management. I had to do a lot of thinking but a couple of years in; I think it was one of the best decisions I have ever made. It’s a great time to be an engineer now with all the amazing technology advancements and tools, but I am glad I was able to identify that I belonged in the product management group. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having an engineering background is a great thing for product managers working on complex tech products. There are some cons, but those are very easy to overcome. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a product manager, I learned how to make decisions and what it takes to build successful products. Success doesn't come just by building a perfectly good product. It involves an orchestrated effort from every other department (sales, marketing, service etc). I am stating the obvious here but working on all the different parts with different team members with products in different stages and more importantly failing a good number of times taught me so many things. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Enterprise software is sexy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building good enterprise software is challenging. After decades of bad reputation set by the likes of IBM and Oracle where they had really awful software that everyone hated, things have a changed a lot for good. The expectations of buyers at enterprises have changed a lot in the recent years and thanks mainly to many of the disrupting startups that have changed the rules of the game. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, it is hard to explain what you do to your grandparents or even your parents but being a part of a product that has the opportunity to have a meaning impact on several businesses is a great thing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Selling is an art&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my initial days as an engineer, I had a big blind screen in front of me and I was one of those engineers who don't generally appreciate the world of sales and marketing. Even thought it was a small company, I had very little visibility on the things that happened outside my department. I wanted to change that and once in every 2-3 weeks, I started sitting in random sales calls and customer meetings. I would just sit and listen and the insights I got proved to be very helpful in many aspects of the job I was doing then.  Monetate had a great head of sales at that time and it was inspiring to see the way in which he built, trained and coached his team. I started appreciating the art of selling, the power of a good sales team and all the little big details. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The importance of good communication is undervalued&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Communication is hard. When a startup has less than 50 people, internal communication isn’t something that needs a lot of attention. Everyone except the sales team will probably be in the same physical location and everyone knows each other by first name. I wonder if there is a startup Dunbar number. With yammer, slack, email and a weekly all-hands meeting, it isn’t hard to keep the team informed of what’s happening. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a point on the growth curve where things start breaking and internal silos get formed. New departments and new offices will start popping up and things will happen so fast, proper communication is the glue that holds everyone together. It isn’t a single person’s job and every department starting with engineering and product has a very important part to play. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Being an immigrant startup employee is complicated&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this isn’t something that applies to a majority of the people who work at startups, it had a profound impact for me. In a nation where first and second-generation immigrants have founded a significant percentage of companies especially in the tech sector, it is a sad reality that it is very complicated and hard for immigrants to work at startups. Out of the few hundred people Monetate hired over several years, I was the only employee who required a visa and this made things a little complicated at times. My managers and the leadership were very supportive in every single way possible and that helped a lot.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does cost a non-trivial amount in legal and government fees and it isn’t a one-time expenditure. Between applications, verifications, renewals, transfers, perm filings it adds up. Besides the cost, it takes a lot of time and attention. During my first application, we had to prove that Monetate was a real company and the job was real! Obviously the government has all the safeguards for fraud prevention. Random things like a small layoff will have an impact on the permanent residence application.  The employee is the only person who has to stay on top of every single detail and it is very taxing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Understand your stock options&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the bay area, every social gathering with people working in technology sector will have a story about how they or someone who they know made a lot of money from stock options or missed the biggest opportunity of their life. In Philadelphia, those stories don’t exist yet. The majority of the folks I worked with had very little knowledge on how options worked. With exits becoming rare and considering the time factor, my general rule of thumb is to consider stock option grants as a nice piece of paper which has little to no value. If there is an upside, it is well and good. If there isn’t one, you just move on. I think it is very important for all startup employees who hold options to understand all the implications so that they can make informed decisions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Be Kind.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a product manager at a growth stage startup, the ultimate goal is to ensure the success of the product and that would involve interacting with almost every department in the company. In this process, it is very easy to spread thin and lose focus. One hard thing every PM will have to do is learning to say ‘no’ to a good number of things and focusing on the right things. Even if there was no intention, it is very easy to offend someone or at worst sound mean. The line between being confident and being arrogant is very thin. While this applies everywhere and not just in a startup setting, the most important thing is to be kind. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monetate was a mature startup and cared about the work-life balance of its employees. It wasn’t one of those places where people spent crazy long hours in the office. However, it is sugar coated, a growth stage startup is a high-pressure work environment for many. It is much easier to be kind when I try to see things from the other person’s perspective. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been thinking about for a while and a few months back, I read a post by Andrew Bosworth and I really liked this part&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Being kind isn’t the same as being nice. It isn’t about superficial praise. It doesn’t mean dulling your opinions. And it shouldn’t diminish the passion with which you present them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Being kind is fundamentally about taking responsibility for your impact on the people around you. It requires you be mindful of their feelings and considerate of the way your presence affects them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is undoubtedly the biggest lesson I learned.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Fixing the high skilled immigration problem</title><link href="/fixing-the-high-skilled-immigration-problem.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-04-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>ram</name></author><id>tag:,2013-04-17:fixing-the-high-skilled-immigration-problem.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is an undeniable fact that immigrants play an important role in the tech industry not just in silicon valley but throughout the country. Be it a small startup with 20 people trying to innovate something or a big corporation with thousands of employees, it is very common to find people at various levels in an organization working on a visa. Every year on the 1st of April, 65000 H1B visas (an additional 20000 for those with advanced degrees from the US) are made available. There have been a number of proposals to increase this number substantially with reforms and there are bills &lt;a href="#fn1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fn2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; in the senate which are in progress for this issue.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These 85000 visas are in high demand and they are issued on a first come first served basis until the cap is reached. The exception is when more than 85000 applications are submitted with the first 5 days. This happened last in 2008 when the economy was booming and it has happened again. For the FY 2014, the number of applications submitted was more than the the number of visas available. USCIS made a &lt;a href="http://www.uscis.gov/portal/site/uscis/menuitem.5af9bb95919f35e66f614176543f6d1a/?vgnextoid=c91dea8c9eadd310VgnVCM100000082ca60aRCRD&amp;amp;vgnextchannel=68439c7755cb9010VgnVCM10000045f3d6a1RCRD"&gt;press release&lt;/a&gt; stating that 124000 applications were received for the 85000 slots and they will be giving away those visa a random selection process aka the "Lottery". To resonate the impact of this situation, i just picked a couple of quotes from a discussion thread on Hacker News. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have a coworker who is an unbelievably talented and respected developer both at my company and in the open source community. He has been working on a student visa after he graduated from an Ivy League school in computer science last year&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That the U.S. is even considering deporting him is batshit crazy to me&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;- &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5514313"&gt;jdross&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is insane. Despite getting in by April 1st we're now waiting on the lottery results to see if our first engineering hire can stay in the country. It's going to be extremely disruptive both to him and to us if he can't stay. Stupid&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-&lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5514504"&gt;acgourley&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Distribution of H1B Visas&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even before thinking about bringing reforms to this broken system, it is important to understand where the visas go right now and how the system is being gamed. I am quoting some points from an answer on Quora which i wrote last year for the question &lt;a href="http://www.quora.com/H1B-Visa-1/What-effect-will-the-2013-H1B-run-out-have-on-the-tech-industry/answer/Ram-Parthasarathy"&gt;"H1B Visa: What effect will the 2013 H1B run-out have on the tech industry?"&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rough split of where the H1B visa goes is as follows&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The big Indian outsourcing firms (tcs, infosys, cts, wipro etc) who want to bring their employees on cheap labor on a long term basis to their client sites. This category forms one of the biggest parts of the pie.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The big tech companies like Microsoft, Google, FB and numerous other companies across different sectors who hire international students. Some of these visas will be applied under the 65000 general quota since the student wouldn't have graduated when the companies extend an offer. The degree certificate is needed to apply under the Master's quota (20000 visas).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tech consulting shops (a lot of fraudulent ones) get a large number of visas. They are listed as the employer in the visa but the person will generally be contracting for another company and the consulting shop generally takes a big cut from the consulting fees. This is one way how people who don't go to school in the US get their foot in the country.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;USCIS makes all the H1B data publicly available every year and it is very evident that currently H1B is just being used as an outsourcing visa. There isn't a single "proper US company"&lt;a href="#fn3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt; in the top ten list. Microsoft corporation stands at number 11 with 1497 visas for the 2012 FY. This interesting &lt;a href="http://deepakbala.me/2012/08/26/analyzing-h1b-data-with-python-and-pandas/"&gt;H1B data analysis&lt;/a&gt; by Deepak Bala also gives a very good perspective of the current state of affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class = "center-img"&gt;

    &lt;img alt ="H1B Top Employers" src = "/img/post-images/h1btop10.png"&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 
        Source : &lt;a href="http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9236732/The_data_shows_Top_H_1B_users_are_offshore_outsourcers"&gt;Computerworld&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class = "center-img"&gt;

    &lt;img alt ="H1B Top Companies" src = "/img/post-images/h1bcompanies.png"&gt;&lt;/img&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 
        Source : &lt;a href="http://deepakbala.me/2012/08/26/analyzing-h1b-data-with-python-and-pandas/"&gt;Deepak Bala&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Definition of High Skilled Labor&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big question in the minds of most people is if there is really a shortage of talent in the US forcing companies to hire internationals or is it an artificially created thing. There is definitely a storage of high skilled labor in technology but it is very hard to term what exactly constitutes a person as highly skilled. According to USCIS, it is someone who has a bachelor's degree in the relevant field and already has a job offer from a company who is willing to pay the person above the prevailing wage&lt;a href="#fn4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt; in that region. So, the following people are all classified as 'high skilled' and compete for the H1B in the same pool. There is no demarcation or a points based system followed by many other countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a PhD from Standford working on Google's automated car&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a graduate with a master's degree in computer science working on Amazon's infrastructure &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a computer engineering graduate building wearable electronic devices at a stealth silicon valley startup &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the more common software engineer or analyst at small-medium sized businesses and fortune 500 companies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a project lead from Wipro responsible for the operations of the onsite team at the client's venue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an employee from infosys/cts/tcs testing and writing bug reports for a 20 year old mainframe system for a big box retailer. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These 6 broad categories will mostly cover 90-95% of the applicant pool. In addition, a small percentage of physicians, medical residents and skilled professionals from non technology sectors also depend on the H1B visa. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Fixing the broken system&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increasing the number of available visas isn't going to fix anything. In fact, a blind increase will make way for more outsourced cheap labor resulting in a situation worse than what we have right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some suggestions to bring some sanity to the high skilled immigration problem. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prevent companies who employ more than 50 percent of its employees in the United States in H-1B or L from obtaining more H1B visas.&lt;/strong&gt; In 2010, the Public Law 111-230&lt;a href="#fn5"&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt; was signed by President Obama which requires an additional fee of $2000 for every petition from such companies. This amount is really insignificant for multi-billion dollar corporations like TCS and Infosys working on long term multi-million dollar contracts for US clients. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will not only stop the outsourcing shops from bringing in more cheap labor but also encourage them to hire locally. It could result in tens of thousands of new entry level technology jobs in the next 5 to 10 years. Most of these jobs are in testing and maintenance and it wouldn't take long to train entry level CS and IT graduates to be ready for the job. In my opinion, taking this step alone will alleviate the issue and move things forward in a nice way.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implement a points based system&lt;/strong&gt; that gives more weightage to applicants with advanced degrees, higher income levels, small businesses etc. The UK Border Agency's &lt;a href="http://www.ukba.homeoffice.gov.uk/visas-immigration/working/whocanuse/"&gt;points based system&lt;/a&gt; can be used as a good reference sheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow H1B holders to start companies&lt;/strong&gt;. While it is theoretically possible for H1B visa holders to start companies it is not a very practical solution. The rule is that a H1B holder can start a company but she can't work for it. While it may sound totally illogical, there are strong reasons behind that rule. There needs to be a employer-employee relationship where the former should be able to terminate the employment of the latter and this relationship will vanish if the h1b holder is a major stakeholder in the business. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more practical solution will be to allow the H1B holder to transfer the visa to an incubator or a VC firm for a short time period (12-24 months) and upon success or failure of the company, the visa can be transfered to the startup or to another company respectively. The VC firm or the incubator won't have any real obligation similar to a university's role in the post graduation OPT work authorization. If the startup is on a good track it will have a board established by then who will then be able to terminate the founder. This may sound a little too complicated but with a proper framework and rules it can be devised well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The probability of a new Google or Ebay is very very low but this will pave the way for thousands of new startups. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Split the available visas into two or three lots per year&lt;/strong&gt; and be flexible with the starting date. Currently the applications can be submitted starting only on April 1st and the starting date can only be after October 1st. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a big roadblock for companies who want to directly hire people living in other countries. If Quora finds a suitable candidate from India or Romania in the next code sprint or Google interviews at top universities in other countries and decides to extend an offer this summer, they cannot start working until October 1, 2014 unless they find a different visa which will allow the person to work inside the US. A year and a half (even 6-8 months) is a really long time for hiring decisions and this is especially true for startups. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this may result in a significant administrative overhead for the USCIS, this will be very helpful for the companies. An additional fee if the application isn't submitted in the lot 1 is a possible solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Substantially increase the fee for companies that have more than 500 employees on visas&lt;/strong&gt;. Microsoft proposed a &lt;a href="http://www.geekwire.com/2013/h1b-visas-tech-companies-divided-plan-higher-fees/"&gt;$10000 additional fee&lt;/a&gt; for H1Bs and a $15000 fee for green cards. Most employers will be ready to pay this fee and this will be a nice additional revenue source for the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a more realistic prevailing wage&lt;a href="#fn4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt; requirement or set a new minimum wage band for H1B applicants. This will ensure that existing tech workers aren't &lt;a href="http://www.motherjones.com/politics/2013/02/silicon-valley-h1b-visas-hurt-tech-workers"&gt;displaced by h1b workers&lt;/a&gt; at a lower wage.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implement stringent checks to prevent misuse and fraud&lt;/strong&gt;. There are a number of bodyshops who obtain h1b visas, serve as a middle man and take a cut. This is bad for the client, bad for the employee and bad for everyone involved except the bodyshop. While there are many genuine consulting businesses utilizing visa workers, the operations of a majority of these consulting companies are fraudulent. The USCIS is very well aware of this practice but has failed to take any action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: I have been writing this post in parts over the past 3-4 weeks and a few nice developments have started in the meantime. Most notable one is the &lt;a href="http://fwd.us"&gt;fwd.us&lt;/a&gt; initiative from many well known tech leaders including Mark Zuckerberg. The gang of eight's new immigration bill also has some good proposals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name = "fn1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.govtrack.us/congress/bills/113/s169#overview"&gt;I-Squared Act of 2013&lt;/a&gt; is a proposal for increasing the visa limits and also providing work authorization for dependents of the visa holder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name = "fn2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.govtrack.us/congress/bills/113/s600/text"&gt;H-1B and L-1 Visa Reform Act of 2013&lt;/a&gt; proposes modifications of the requirements and also the review procedure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name = "fn3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt; The top 10 in that list are registered US companies but they are primarily Indian outsourcing companies with a presence in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name = "fn4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt; Prevailing wage is a minimum annual or hourly wage required for a H1B worker. This wage requirement is generally quoted from &lt;a href="http://www.flcdatacenter.com/OESQuick.aspx"&gt;Foreign Labor Certification Data Center&lt;/a&gt;. While some of the quoted wages are inline with the market rates, there are certainly loopholes where a software engineer who gets paid 75K in the bay area is eligible for a H1B visa which is definitely in the lowest end of the bracket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name = "fn5"&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.uscis.gov/USCIS/Laws/Memoranda/2011/Public_Law_111-230_Memo.pdf"&gt;Public Law 111-230&lt;/a&gt; (pdf) increased the fee for outsourcing companies by $2000 for every petition. &lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Static blog using pelican and github pages</title><link href="/static-blog-using-pelican-and-github-pages.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>ram</name></author><id>tag:,2012-10-01:static-blog-using-pelican-and-github-pages.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last six years, i have blogged in many different places both for fun and profit. It helped me meet many interesting folks through blog meets and various conferences and in the journey i also made some great friends. In the recent times, i completely stopped writing and publishing my thoughts. Thanks to twitter, there was always a place to express one's thoughts in a short and fast manner. Even though i had a couple of dormant blogs, i didn't feel like publishing there when i wanted to. Hopefully, this new setup will change that. After spending some time and exploring a few different options, i decided to go with &lt;a href="http://pelican.notmyidea.org/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew i wanted a static blog and also one than ran on python rather than ruby. So, that eliminated the more popular static blog generators like Jekyll, Octopress framework and many more. There are a few other python based static blog generators that work well out of the box and are more popular than Pelican but i liked the configurability of Pelican and the ease of writing a custom theme using Jinja templates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were the basic requirements that i had&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write posts in Markdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy templating and theming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic command line tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setup the blog as a local git repository and push to github&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy publishing to S3, Github or Heroku&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I created two git repositories, one to hold all the scripts and setup files from Pelican and the other to hold the static content. Currently i am publishing the static blog to the free and wonderful Github Pages. If you create a username.github.com repo in your account, github will automatically generate and publish the content in the master branch. I used &lt;a href="http://docs.fabfile.org/en/1.4.3/index.html"&gt;Fabric&lt;/a&gt; to completely automate this process. Whenever, i write a new post or make changes to the theme, all i have to do is type in 'fab publish' and it does a few sequential steps and pushes the master branch to origin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the templates from the base theme and made a custom theme. Thanks to media queries, the site is now responsive and is readable on tablets and touch phones. I still have to make some more tweaks and refinements in that department though. The thing i like about this setup is it wouldn't be very hard to switch over to a different static blog generator in the future if i want to. Eventhough it took a good amount of time to get the blog up and running, it was definitely a satisfying experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://pelican.notmyidea.org/en/3.0/index.html#documentation"&gt;Pelican docs&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://martinbrochhaus.com/2012/02/pelican.html"&gt;A good intro to publishing with pelican&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://help.github.com/categories/20/articles"&gt;Github pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary></entry></feed>