<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Ram Parthasarathy</title><link href="ramanuj.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="ramanuj.me/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>ramanuj.me/</id><updated>2012-10-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Static blog using pelican and github pages</title><link href="ramanuj.me/static-blog-using-pelican-and-github-pages.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-10-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>ram</name></author><id>tag:ramanuj.me,2012-10-01:static-blog-using-pelican-and-github-pages.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last six years, i have blogged in many different places both for fun and profit. It helped me meet many interesting folks through blog meets and various conferences and in the journey i also made some great friends. In the recent times, i completely stopped writing and publishing my thoughts. Thanks to twitter, there was always a place to express one's thoughts in a short and fast manner. Even though i had a couple of dormant blogs, i didn't feel like publishing there when i wanted to. Hopefully, this new setup will change that. After spending some time and exploring a few different options, i decided to go with &lt;a href="http://pelican.notmyidea.org/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew i wanted a static blog and also one than ran on python rather than ruby. So, that eliminated the more popular static blog generators like Jekyll, Octopress framework and many more. There are a few other python based static blog generators that work well out of the box and are more popular than Pelican but i liked the configurability of Pelican and the ease of writing a custom theme using Jinja templates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were the basic requirements that i had&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write posts in Markdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy templating and theming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic command line tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setup the blog as a local git repository and push to github&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy publishing to S3, Github or Heroku&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I created two git repositories, one to hold all the scripts and setup files from Pelican and the other to hold the static content. Currently i am publishing the static blog to the free and wonderful Github Pages. If you create a username.github.com repo in your account, github will automatically generate and publish the content in the master branch. I used &lt;a href="http://docs.fabfile.org/en/1.4.3/index.html"&gt;Fabric&lt;/a&gt; to completely automate this process. Whenever, i write a new post or make changes to the theme, all i have to do is type in 'fab publish' and it does a few sequential steps and pushes the master branch to origin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the templates from the base theme and made a custom theme. Thanks to media queries, the site is now responsive and is readable on tablets and touch phones. I still have to make some more tweaks and refinements in that department though. The thing i like about this setup is it wouldn't be very hard to switch over to a different static blog generator in the future if i want to. Eventhough it took a good amount of time to get the blog up and running, it was definitely a satisfying experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://pelican.notmyidea.org/en/3.0/index.html#documentation"&gt;Pelican docs&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://martinbrochhaus.com/2012/02/pelican.html"&gt;A good intro to publishing with pelican&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://help.github.com/categories/20/articles"&gt;Github pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary></entry></feed>